Philip Kappel Papers
Philip Kappel Papers
1932-1966
Kappel, Philip.
1.0 linear ft.
Papers of the American etcher, illustrator, author (1901-1981). Typescript drafts, revisions, and galley proofs for Jamaica Gallery; articles, reviews, and clippings (1932-1966); exhibition catalogs (1941-1966); and 2 photographs.
149596
Biographical History
Philip Kappel (1901-1981) was an American artist, art collector, and author. Born in Connecticut, Kappel worked in a variety of media including etching and illustrating and wrote several books and essays.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Philip Kappel Papers consists of biographical material, correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia.
Correspondence consists of two incoming letters, one from Buckingham Palace acknowledging the Queen of England's receipt of Kappel's book Jamaica Gallery. Artwork contains three original etchings and a few reproductions (personal greeting cards and a dust jacket for Timothy Dexter Revisited by John P. Marquand). Writings include typescript drafts with revisions, galley proofs, and an introduction by Marquand for the book Jamaica Gallery, a book dummy of New England Gallery, and a published essay about Kappel's 18th century house.
Memorabilia comprises photographs and printed material. Photographs depict Kappel in his studio and home, and at a ceremony at Trinity College in which he received an honorary Doctor of Fine Arts degree. Printed material encompasses articles and reviews (1932-1965); newspaper clippings (1932-1966); an exhibit catalog (1966) of 18th and 19th century Japanese prints which Kappel arranged and selected from his personal collection; exhibition catalogs including Kappel's work (1941-1966); an exhibit invitation; and book publicity.
Arrangement of the Collection
Alphabetically by title and/or type.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Illustrators; Art -- Painters; Kappel, Philip.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Etchers -- United States.; Illustrators -- United States.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Drafts (documents); Etchings (prints); Exhibition catalogs.; Galley proofs.; Photographs.; Artists.; Etchers.; Illustrators.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Bigoraphical material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - [General], 1960; 1961 (Box 1)
- Artwork
  - Original etchings, undated; 3 items (Oversize 1)
    Gift of Clyde "Sandy" Morris, 2017.
  - Reproductions, 1951; 1960,; undated (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Jamaica Gallery, typescript drafts with revisions, galley proofs (Box 1)
    - New England Gallery, dummy (Box 1)
  - Essays
    - "Washington Never Slept Here," The New England Galaxy, Winter 1964 (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Photographs
    - Miscellaneous, 1955-1966; undated (Box 1)
      One item gift of Clyde "Sandy" Morris, 2017.
  - Printed material
    - Articles, reviews, 1932-1965; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1932-1966; undated (Box 1)
    - Exhibition catalog: "Exhibition of Japanese Prints by 18th and 19th Century Masters" (arranged and selected by Philip Kappel from his personal collection), 1966 (Box 1)
    - Exhibition catalogs, 1941-1947; 1963,; 1966 (Box 1)
    - Exhibition invitation, 1961 (Box 1)
    - Programs, 1966; "Inauguration of Albert Edward Holland as President of Hobart and William Smith Colleges" (Kappel served as delegate of Pratt Institute), and "140th Commencement of Trinity College" (Kappel received honorary degree) (Box 1)
    - Publicity (book), undated (Box 1)